So we today's דף נ"ה Daf Nun Hey 55. We're going to
wrap up the fifth פרק perek and begin the sixth and final
פרק perek on the ארבע אבות נזיקין. Arba Avos Nezikin. This פרק
perek has been pretty much devoted almost solely to בור, Bor, but
then the last משנה Mishna mentioned that the שור וחמור shor v'chamor
referred to in בור Bor is not to be understood limited to
those two animals; it really refers to all animals, mostly because by
שבת Shabbos it's clear that it refers to all animals. And then
it says that by many, many places in the תורה Torah where
are mentioned things like שור או חמור shor o chamor or things
of that nature, it really includes all animals. Now, the one thing
normally it's like, okay fine, includes everything. But the one thing that
the משנה Mishna mentioned that's going to require more clarification now that
we've broadened the category is
כלאים, kilayim, either when you have the ox and donkey plowed together,
חורש בשור וחמור, choresh b'shor v'chamor, or crossbreeding. So if now it
includes all animals, well, what is the line of distinction between different
species of animals? So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
וכן חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן v'chen chayah v'of k'yotzei bahen דף נ"ה
עמוד א', Daf Nun Hey Amud Aleph, three lines down in the
wide lines. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, says ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, כאן שנה רבי, kan shana Rebbi, here רבי Rebbi has taught
us that תרנגול טווס ופסיוני, tarnegol tavas u'pisyoni, a chicken, a peacock,
and a פסיוני, pisyoni, which is some type of, I don't know,
how does it translate it? A partridge.
What? A partridge?
A partridge is different than a peacock? That shows how much I
know. Okay fine. Any pear trees going around? It could be a
pheasant. A pheasant. Okay fine. So a chicken, a peacock, and a—at
least I know what a pheasant is, or at least I heard
the word before—and a
pheasant. Okay. שליו, שליו. slav, slav. Okay right. Where are we? On
נ"ה עמוד א', Nun Hey Amud Aleph, three lines down in the
wide lines, or four lines now. כלאים זה בזה kilayim zeh b'zeh
are כלאים kilayim if you mix, if you crossbreed them. Okay. Now,
now, the תוספות Tosafos points out that רבי Rebbi didn't teach that
anywhere in the משנה. Mishna. רבי Rebbi just said that all species
are included in the איסור issur of כלאים. kilayim. He didn't teach
how to draw the lines between the species. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos
says it's really like a literary flourish. It means based on what
רבי Rebbi has now taught us, that the idea of כלאים kilayim
extends to all
animals, now there's going to be some real ramifications of this. And
now we're going to determine what are the different species, but based
on this, we're going to think these animals, these species which are
pretty close to one another, are all considered different species in their
כלאים. kilayim. So now it becomes the question: how do you draw
the line? What defines a different species? So the גמרא Gemara actually
says, I mean the גמרא Gemara interestingly says פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious.
I don't know how obvious it is. No, אמר רב חביבא, Amar
Rav Chaviva, maybe because they have different names, so it's obvious they're
different species. אמר רב חביבא משום דרבו בהדי הדדי Amar Rav Chaviva
mishum d'rabu behadi hadadei because they grow up amongst one another, they
mate? No, not mate. I think it means that they just live
together.
What?
I don't know, but that's not what רבו rabu means here. מהו
דתימא מין
חד הוא, mahu d'teima min chad hu, I think it's an interesting
question. If animals naturally crossbreed, what the footnote says it means that
they do breed with one another?
Yeah, it says
the
רמב"ם Rambam
says
seems to understand the גמרא Gemara as meaning that these species are
capable of
bearing—capable of mating with one another. Interesting. But רבו rabu more naturally
means just that they
grow up together, right? So but they live together. But that's interesting
because they're capable of crossbreeding, right? I mean if you could imagine
that animals that couldn't—I mean, I don't know what capable means. Capable
means by—left to their own devices, you could physically make it happen
if you put the pieces together. But okay, but I hear the
point. If they sort of might have the potential normal potential of
crossbreeding. That's an interesting read.
That has to do with whether their offsprings are fertile or not.
Yeah, but not only, you have the mule, which is a horse
and a donkey, right? So that's not a fertile offspring. Okay. דרבו
בהדי הדדי, d'rabu behadi hadadei, so they grow up with one another,
or maybe they have the capability of crossbreeding. So מהו דתימא מין
חד הוא, mahu d'teima min chad hu, it's one
מין, min, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that that is not
sufficient to do that. They're actually, if memory serves me correctly, there
was a whole interesting question about the כשרות kashrus of
turkeys because turkey's a New World bird. So and normally by birds
we say that we have to have a מסורה, masorah, it's not
just that they have the
right physical characteristics, we need a tradition that they're not one of
the birds mentioned in the תורה. Torah. So something that was a
New World bird, how do you have a מסורה masorah it's not
one of them mentioned in the—of course you could say if it's
a New World bird, that's why it wasn't mentioned in the תורה
Torah because nobody who was living in the Middle East knew about
turkeys. But anyway, one of the arguments—it's actually quite fascinating because one
of—I think that they got the name—this is all just from the
top of my head memory, this is probably all wrong—but anyway, I
think it got the name turkey because it was brought by people
who traded. It was traded like through Turkish traders, and that's where
first they brought them in through the New World,
but I think because of that name it led people, some people
to believe that it was an old world bird and that they
did have a tradition around it. So actually like there's a false
מסורה mesorah that grew up around the turkey. Anyway, the only reason
I mention it is because some wanted to argue that since it
grows up together with kosher birds and it lives together with kosher
birds, this גמרא Gemara about רובו ובהדי הדדי rubo vehadei hadei should
that be a sufficient evidence that fundamentally it's מין אחד min echad
and that that would be enough of an evidence that it would
be a kosher bird. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says for
כלאים kilayim that is not and you could have animals that live
together maybe even have the possibility of crossbreeding and are still כלאים.
kilayim. Of course it doesn't tell us where to draw the lines.
So that would be the next גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look.
אמר
שמואל, amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, אווז, avaz, a goose ואווז הבר
ve’avaz habar and a wild goose, כלאים זה בזה. kilayim zeh bazeh.
Now that's getting interesting, right? Because things that basically are called the
same thing and just seems to be a subspecies and are defined
to be כלאים. kilayim.
Rose by any other names, no not at all.
Very good. So מתקיף לה רבה בר בר חנה, matkif lah Ravva
bar bar Chanan, מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama? What's the reason? אילימא משום
דהאי אריך קועיה ileima mishum dehai arich kavei one has a long
beak והאי זוטר קועיה vehai zutar kavei and the other has a
short beak? So אלא מעתה, ella me’ata, if that's true, so meaning
what, is there just like a different physical characteristic? I mean that
would be crazy, right? Them every subspecies variation because normally a subspecies
variation has to do with some type of physical characteristic difference, everything
is כלאים? kilayim? So אלא מעתה ella me’ata if that's true,
גמלא פרסא, gamla parsa, a Persian camel, which is a dromedary, and
גמלא טייא, gamla taya, an Arabian... oh no, a גמלא טייא gamla
taya is an Arabian camel. Arabian camel is the dromedary. Now I
don't know what a Persian camel is. I looked it up, apparently
there's only two species of camels. The dromedary, the one hump and
the two humps. The dromedary and the other one is called the,
I forget, it starts with a B. Yes, Bactrian. Thank you. Camel,
which comes from like Asia and China and Mongolia and those that
that area. So that's not, so that's not what it means by
Persian camel. Anyway, and it's clearly not the difference because the גמרא'ס
Gemara’s not going to say that the difference is one hump and
two humps. So it might be some subspecies difference within the Arabian
dromedary camels. So if that's true that that that things is enough
to make it a different
species. So דהאי אלים קועיה, dehai alim kavei, now it's the same
word here קועיה kavei which means the beak. רש"י Rashi I think
says that this קועיה kavei here means the hump. That one, oh
no the neck רש"י Rashi says. This has a this has a
thick neck, והאי קטין קועיה vehai katin kavei and the other one
has a thin neck. So הכי נמי דהוי כלאים זה בזה? hachi
nami dehavi kilayim zeh bazeh? Would you also say it's כלאים? kilayim?
And that's absurd. I don't know how that's more absurd than the
geese, but somehow the גמרא Gemara knew that that couldn't be. Like
how far are you going to take this? Any subspecies with a
slightly different physical attribute, you know, after attribute? So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא אמר אביי, ella amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, זה ביציו
מבחוץ וזה ביציו מבפנים. zeh beitzav mibachutz vezeh beitzav mibifnim. Now the
difference is that in one of it the...
getting back to the geese, right? You know the testicles are on
the inside and the other they are on the outside. So that's
seen as presumably significant because that's, you know, the relating to the
mating, right? And relates to so the idea of the procreation. So
maybe that's more significant because it's a sexual characteristic and that makes
it a different... Okay, but again like it doesn't tell us broad
principles. I remember somebody wrote a very, I have to dig it
up, but you know some scientist wrote a whole big article going
through מסכת כלאים Masechet Kilayim and the, you know, the משניות Mishnayot
and these גמרות Gemaras and whatever and trying to figure out like
any try at some systematic, you know, difference, definition of what are
different species for חז"ל Chazal for כלאים. kilayim. I think in the
end he wasn't able to come up with anything. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, but here at least it's something that's
seen as, you know, significant and again maybe specifically because it's a
sexual characteristic. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב פפא
אמר, Rav Pappa amar, האי טעונה חדא ביעתא בשחלא hai teuna chada
beita beshichla and here again is a sexual or procreative difference. האי
טעונה, hai teuna, again going between these different geese, האי טעונה חדא
ביעתא בשחלא, hai teuna chada beita beshichla, one of them carries one
egg in its cluster, והאי טעונה כמה ביעתא בשחלא, vehai teuna kama
beita beshichla, and the other carries multiple eggs in its cluster, so
you know as it's laying them it could have multiple eggs inside
that it's sort of dropping them you know sequentially but it doesn't
have to it doesn't like only sort of like start hibernating or
whatever it's called growing that's the wrong word anyway developing the other
egg inside of its body only after one of them is laid
it can do them multiple at the same time. So again it
seems like things that are different in terms of sexual or procreative
characteristics are particularly significant. Okay, אמר רבי ירמיה אמר ריש לקיש. amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Reish Lakish. So says רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah in
the name of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. המרביע שני מינים שבים, hamarbei
shenei minim shebayam, remember we said that כל בהמה kol behema includes
all animals and we included birds, right? You might remember we included
birds. What we did not explicitly address was the issue of fish,
right? So are you allowed to work your fish on
שבת? Shabbos? So so מינים שבים minim shebayam is not just limited
to fish it could also include like mammals in the sea or
whatever you know dolphins can you get your I don't know if
you've got tame dolphins can you get them to pull a boat
on שבת Shabbos or something. So now we're talking about if you
crossbreed So תוספות Tosafos makes the point of saying מרביע Marbia here
we have to be talking not about fish because fish don't have
sexual reproduction. We're talking about like, you know, mammals, you know, some
type of sea mammal. Okay, so המרביע שני מינים שבים HaMarbia Shenei
Minim SheBaYam if you crossbreed two types of sea animals,
לוקה, lokei, you get lashes. מאי טעמא, Mai Taama, what's the reason?
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה משמיה דעולא, Amar Rav Ada Bar Ahava
Mishmei DeUlla, אתיא למינהו למינהו מיבשה Atya LiMinehu LiMinehu MiYabasha because it
says by, you know, by the, by the dry animals, animals of
the dry lands, it says, hold on, let's see רש״י, Rashi, רש״י
Rashi says,
oh does רש״י Rashi claim it?
So yeah, so it says right, it says by, by מעשה בראשית,
Maaseh Bereishis, it says that you know, God created these animals למינהו,
LiMinehu, each one according to their species, and it says that also
by the fish, that they were created למינהו, LiMinehu, which is an
indication that they need to keep by their separate species. So since
we know that there's an איסור issur of כלאים kilayim by the
dry animal, by the animals of the land, because there it says
בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים. Behemtecha Lo Tarbia Kilayim. It's very interesting, you
know, because what we're doing here is there's no explicit פסוק pasuk
in the story of בראשית Bereishis where it says you have an
obligation to keep these to their separate species.
So it's not just the fact that it uses the word למינהו
LiMinehu is a sufficient basis for inferring a prohibition of crossbreeding. תוספות
Tosafos actually here has here a discussion: are we to infer from
this that בני נח Bnei Noach are אסור assur to crossbreed? Because
there actually is a debate in the גמרא Gemara whether שבע מצוות
בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach include, or you know, be more
than seven, but include the איסור issur of כלאים kilayim based on
the word למינהו. LiMinehu. So is the word למינהו LiMinehu enough by
itself to say you must keep these animals למינהו? LiMinehu? And תוספות
Tosafos says not necessarily. If there's no prohibition, then God just created
them למינהו, LiMinehu, it doesn't say you have to keep that. But
now what we're doing is, and this is really I always find
like interesting, like it's sort of like, you know, when theology sort
of intersects with הלכה. halacha. You have a פסוק pasuk that describes
like מעשה בראשית. Maaseh Bereishis. God created למינהו. LiMinehu. That doesn't tell
you you have to keep things that way. Then you've got this
other פסוק pasuk that says don't crossbreed. Okay, well, don't crossbreed, what
should be the scope of that? Okay,
בהמתך, behemtecha, don't crossbreed animals, right, and even has a word that
says animals like בהמתך behemtecha which are like terrestrial animals. But it
tells you well what's the scope of that? Well, if you look
back in this totally non-halachic section of the תורה Torah about מעשה
בראשית, Maaseh Bereishis, it says there's an idea of keeping every animal
to its own species. Oh, so let's figure out that when it
says בהמתך behemtecha it means not only land animals, it means even
fish, because we're told in מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishis that fish are
created למינהו. LiMinehu. So I think that's like really interesting, you know,
in terms of how that sort of almost like this theological, you
know, sort of narrative here, you know, is influencing the scope of
a מצווה. mitzvah. It's interesting, you know, nowadays also because people ask
about questions about, what do you call it, like cloning and those
types of issues, and you know some people say like want to
learn inferences from מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishis and this whole idea of
למינהו LiMinehu about creating new species and is that forbidden, you know,
and so on. And again, that's like a straight theological argument because
there's no exact, you know, they're not trying to plug it into
any prohibition. They're just trying to tell you, you know, the type
of theology that's expressed in those פסוקים psukim should be indicating that
you like shouldn't be creating new species. Okay, but that's like just
the theology argument by itself. Here it's sort of intersecting with a
clear prohibition of crossbreeding, which as Michael correctly says has a very
concrete word בהמתך behemtecha and we're going to broaden it based on
the פסוקים psukim of למינהו. LiMinehu. Yes, Rabbi Dov.
So this verb להרגיע Lehargia is not intrinsically a negative word? Just
means to crossbreed in a neutral sense?
להרביע Learbia I think just means normally I think it means just
the actual act of copulating animals. I don't even know if it
means crossbreed.
So just a verb that describes the sexual act of animals?
Yes, yeah, I'm pretty sure it doesn't even mean crossbreed. Yeah, yeah.
Is the איסור issur the actual crossbreeding or is it to get
הנאה hanaah from the?
No, it is, no, it is the crossbreeding. The only thing that
you can, first of all, they used mules widespread in the ancient
world, right? Have you ever eaten a, just last night I ate
for the first time I think in my life, although I didn't
make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu it wasn't such a big deal, a pluot.
I don't know, pluot, a plum and an apricot. Look at that,
did you make a שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu? You had them before. Anyway, so
what? What is that? It's a plum and an apricot. Oh, I
prefer each one individually I'll tell you. Anyway,
but, so we constantly benefit from כלאים. kilayim. The only כלאים kilayim
you can't actually benefit from is כלאי הכרם kilayei hakerem when it's
with, when it's with the vine. You also not allowed to wear
obviously שעטנז, shatnez, but you know, but fundamentally the כלאים kilayim איסור
issur is not to derive benefit, but it's to do the act
of crossbreeding. It's interesting questions, you know, the things that like, it's
an interesting question, well I'm totally going off topic now but like
בשר בחלב, basar be-chalav, right? לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. Lo Tevashel
Gdi BaChalev Imo. Is that... We constantly focus on don't eat them
together but the תורה Torah says don't cook them together. Is that
fundamentally like an איסור כלאיים? issur kilayim? Like the תורה Torah doesn't
want you to cook them together and as a result, don't eat
it, but it doesn't focus on the איסור issur of eating. Anyway,
so כלאיים kilayim fundamentally focuses on the איסור issur of the bringing
of the together, not of the benefiting from the product.
Okay, so you can't tell somebody else, you just do this כלאיים
kilayim for me or something like that?
Well, that's a general question of, you know, of, like, well, about
like, I mean, if it's a Jew then it's מסייע mesaya or
whatever, it's מחטיא לפני עיוור. machta lifnei iver. If it's a non-Jew
there's a more general question in the גמרא Gemara of is there
אמירה לנכרי amira l'nochri by general איסורים issurim that are not like,
not שבת Shabbos and so on? So, yeah.
But in the horse's case it's too late once they made one
so they stop them, right?
Correct. No, that's correct.
We can't make, you know, right, correct. He's only actively making the
horse.
Right, right, that's correct, meaning that would be a good question, could
you have somebody to breed mules for you? So that's the גמרא's
Gemara's question, I mean, even a non-Jew, whether, whether the איסור issur
of, well, first of all, there's a question whether non-Jews are prohibited
in כלאיים kilayim and then it's a question about whether the איסור
issur of אמירה לנכרי amira l'nochri applies more broadly. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. המרביע שני מינים שבים לוקה. מאי טעמא? רב יהודה בר חביבא
משמיה דעולא, אתיא למיניהו למיניהו מיבשה. Ha'marvia shnei minim she'ba'yam loka. Mai
ta'ama? Rav Yehuda bar Chaviva mishmeih d'Ula, atya l'mineihu l'mineihu mi'yabasha. It
says למיניהו l'mineihu by the dry animals in בראשית Bereishis and it
says by the animals of the sea. בעא רחבא, רחבא בעי. המנהיג
בעיזא ושיבוטא. Ba'a Rechava, Rechava ba'ei. Ha'manhig b'iza v'shibuta. If somebody causes
like, you know,
a goat and a שיבוטא, shibuta, which is some type of a
fish. I do not know how your fish and your goat are
going to both like draw a wagon or something, or you know,
which is what they're doing.
A dolphin and
an ox through the canal? I don't understand how you get like,
what do you do? You get like a rope around the fish?
That's the same word from שבת Shabbos with one of those, one
of the אמוראים Amoraim where like preparing a שיבוטא. shibuta.
I mean, if it's a dolphin I understand, you can get a
dolphin, you put some rope around a dolphin, you get it to
draw, you know, to draw some, to, you know, pull a wagon
or something. A dolphin in the street? No, well, you have, no,
you're walking by the edge of the water. Okay now, you're walking
by the edge of the river, the canal, with your dolphin in
the canal. Anyway, somehow you've got this going on with your fish,
you're having them both together pull some type of a wagon, okay,
or something of that nature. אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava question? What? Right,
it does sound like a רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya question. Okay. מהו?
Mahu? What are we saying? מי אמרינן? Mi amrinan? Do we say,
כיון דעיזא לא נחית בימא ושיבוטא לא סליק ליבשה, לאו כלום עביד?
keivan d'iza lo nachit b'yama v'shibuta lo salik l'yabasha, lav klum avid?
The goat is never going to go into the
ocean and the שיבוטא shibuta is never going to come up to
the dry land. לאו כלום עביד. lav klum avid. You're not really
having them draw together because they're not in the same space, they're
in separate spaces. Okay.
או דילמא? O dilma? Or do we say, השתא מיהא קא מנהיג?
hashta miha ka manhig?
Nevertheless, here now you're having them both sort of draw something together,
you know, and that's the prohibition of כלאיים, kilayim, not cross-breeding, but
having animals together like, you know, draw load together.
So מתקיף לה רבינא, matkif lah Ravina, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if
you say that, חיבר חטה ושעורה בידו, chiber chita u'se'ora b'yado, let's
say you put a barley and a wheat seed in your hand,
וזרע חטה בארץ ושעורה בחוץ לארץ, v'zara chita ba'aretz u'se'ora b'chutz la'aretz,
and the wheat seed fell on ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the
barley seed fell a half an inch over, right over the line,
in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So would you say הכי נמי דמיחייב?
hachi nami d'mechayev? You're only חייב כלאיים, chayav kilayim, it's אסור דרבנן
assur d'rabanan in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but only חייב דאורייתא chayav
d'oraisa in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Clearly, because they're on two sides
of the line that divides them. Here too. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר ליה: הכי השתא? Amar lei: hachi hashta? What type of
answer is that? התם ארץ מקום חיובא, חוץ לארץ לאו מקום חיובא.
Hasam aretz makom chiyuva, chutz la'aretz lav makom chiyuva. The seed that's
in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz is in a place where you're not
prohibited. So of course you're not חייב. chayav. Half of the act
was done in a place where there's no prohibition. הכא האי חיובא
והאי חיובא. Hacha hai chiyuva v'hai chiyuva. You just got through telling
me that you can't do כלאיים kilayim of animals in the water.
So the water is a place where the איסורים issurim of כלאיים
kilayim apply. So if you have one animal in the water and
one on the land, maybe they should be doing כלאיים kilayim even
though they can't ever get into the same zone. Okay. השתא דקא
קא מנהיג. Hashta d'ka ka manhig. That was a slightly humorous...
You can't use my שיבוטא. shibuta.
You can't use your שיבוטא shibuta to draw your wagon, yeah.
As you learn from this that רבינא Ravina did not learn the
art of annoying questions from רב ירמיה. Rav Yirmiya.
There you go, exactly. רחבא ורחבה. Rechava v'Rechava.
Exactly. Okay, moving on. We now transition, we now transition from
a פרק perek devoted to wells,
to בור, bor, to pits, to a פרק perek where the first
one is going to be sort of get us back to שן
ורגל, shen v'regel, but a lot of this פרק perek is going
to be devoted to אש. eish. Okay. So if you think about
it, it was sort of like, you know, we had way in
the beginning שן ורגל, shen v'regel, right? Do you remember those early
פרקים, prakim, you know, כיצד הרגל, Keitzad Ha'regel, etc.? Then we had
a whole middle section devoted to the ox, to the goring oxen
and the שור הנגח shor ha'nagach and the כופר. kofer. We had
אדם המזיק adam ha'mazik sort of scattered in, particularly about the person
who fell, remember all the people running into each other in the
רשות הרבים reshus ha'rabim and hitting each other and tripping over each
other and so on? So אדם המזיק adam ha'mazik was sort of
scattered, but we had like
שן ורגל, shen v'regel, we had
שור. shor. required for שן shein and רגל. regel. So you might
remember we had a משנה mishna about the level of שמירה shemira
for a goring ox. Remember קשרו בעליו במוסרה kesharo be'alav be'mosaira and
that whole weird position of רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, higher level of
שמירה shemira for a תם tam than for a מועד, muad, all
those interesting positions. Then we had the משנה mishna about כיסהו כראוי
kisahu k'rauy by the well, right? One guy covered it, the other
guy passed over it, right? And what happened with the camels and
the cows and the whole thing. So now we're doubling back and
talking about the level of שמירה shemira required for שן shein and
רגל. regel. Let's take a look. Okay. הכונס צאן לדיר, Hakonais tzon
ladir, somebody brings his sheep into the pen, ונעל בפניה כראוי, v'na'al
b'faneha k'rauy, and locks
in front of it appropriately. It's always this generic word in the
משנה: mishna: כיסהו כראוי, kisahu k'rauy, נעל בפניה כראוי. na'al b'faneha k'rauy.
Like, please tell me what כראוי k'rauy is, you know? So presumably
what it seems to be, whatever the standard is, minimum standard, we'll
see. ויצאה והזיקה, V'yatzah v'hizikah, and it goes out and it damages,
פטור, patur, you're exempt. Okay? Once you did your level of שמירה,
shemira, you are exempt. There's a bit of a חידוש chiddush here
because
by the שור shor and by the בור, bor, it says ולא
ישמרנו, v'lo yishmerenu, right? It says by both of those, remember by
בור, bor, what does it say by the בור? bor? It says
כי יפתח איש בור או כי יכרה איש בור ולא יכסנו. Ki
yiftach ish bor o ki yichreh ish bor v'lo yichasenu. It says
ולא יכסנו, v'lo yichasenu, ולא ישמרנו. v'lo yishmerenu. By שן shein and
רגל, regel, which are pretty hidden in the תורה Torah anyway, we
learn it out from ושלח ובער, v'shilach u'vi'er, it never says you
didn't watch it. So there's actually a חידוש, chiddush, if you watched
it, you're exempt. Okay, so if you did the watching and it
got out, you're exempt.
לא נעל בפניה כראוי, Lo na'al b'faneha k'rauy, if he did not
watch it appropriately, ויצאה והזיקה חייב, v'yatzah v'hizikah chayav, and it went
out, you're liable. נפרצה בלילה או שפרצוה ליסטים, Nifretzah balaila o she'pirtzuha
listim, now this is if you watched it correctly and it did
break out at night or if it was
taken out by bandits, ויצאה והזיקה פטור, v'yatzah v'hizikah patur, you're exempt.
Now how does that tell you something more than you've already told
me?
If it's נפרצה, nifretzah, it's unusual, what does it
mean if it's at night or a day? Okay, so that's a
different way of asking. But why are you telling me this that
you didn't tell me before? Before you told me you watched it
appropriately. So one answer gets to what Michael's point is, to tell
me that even if you did it correctly, if it broke out
in the daytime, then you might be liable if we can assume
that you should have by this stage heard about it and you
have an opportunity to do something about it. תוספות Tosafot also says
the flip, which is a very interesting thing about being sort of
accommodating, you know, human weakness. He says if you heard about it
in the middle of the night, you're exempt even if you did
hear about it in the middle of the night. Nobody is expecting
you, maybe if you've got a goring ox on the loose, it's
different. Okay? But nobody is expecting you at 2:00 AM to run
after your sheep, okay, that are wandering and maybe eating from somebody
else's field. Which is interesting, right? How about to what degree the
level of שמירה shemira is not just defined objectively by preventing the
likelihood of certain damage, but it's modulated by what is normal to
expect from people. Like there's a phrase the גמרא Gemara sometimes talks
about, שמרו כדרך השומרים. shamru k'derech ha'shomrim. You did what the norm
was. It might not really have covered all possibilities, but you did
what was normally demanded, okay? So that's a nice idea that even
if you hear about it in the middle of the night, nobody's
demanding that you go and get up in the middle of the
night to do something about it. Yeah.
You shouldn't be expected to go wandering around at 2:00 AM.
Well, that's true.
You mean so as not to put yourself in danger?
Right, that's true. But תוספות, Tosafot, I mean, but that's less of
a חידוש. chiddush. תוספות Tosafot says לא אטרחוהו, lo atrichuhu, they didn't
even make you like go to the effort of doing it, you
know, and even that you'd be is enough to exempt you. Now
the הוציאוה ליסטים hotziuha listim is another חידוש, chiddush, because that says
that even if the bandits, we're going to see in a minute
that as long as the bandits didn't physically take possession of it,
if they just broke it, the fence, in order because they were
either tried to sneak into your house to get something and the
animals wandered off, maybe if they were trying to get the animals
to come out, but they didn't actually do a קניין kinyan to
take possession of the animals, the חידוש chiddush is that the ליסטים
listim are also exempt. Okay, they don't, they don't become the ליסטים's
listim animals either. Okay. הוציאוה ליסטים, Hotziuha listim, now that's if ויצאה
והזיקה, v'yatzah v'hizikah, that's פרצוה ליסטים pirtzuha listim ויצאה והזיקה פטור. v'yatzah
v'hizikah patur. הוציאוה ליסטים, Hotziuha listim, if the bandits actually physically removed
them and thereby took possession, then ליסטים חייבין, listim chayavin, they become
liable. Even though they don't own them, they're only like גנבים ganavim
over them, but nevertheless, as we know, like a שומר, shomer, when
he takes it into his possession, takes responsibility. A גנב ganav as
well, when they take it and they get an ownership, which is
known as a certain type of קנייני גניבה, kinyanei geneivah, and they
are the de facto people that have possessed it and control it,
they become liable for things it does. So if they just broke
the fence and it went out and damaged, they're exempt. If they
took it out, they're liable. Okay? חייבין. Chayavin. הניחה בחמה או שמסרה
לחרש שוטה וקטן. Henichah bachamah o she'mesarah l'cheiresh shoteh v'katan.
Now let's say you locked the fence properly, but it was right
there in the middle of the blazing August sun. Okay? Or you
gave it to a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheiresh shoteh v'katan. In that
case, you can't say, "Hey, I did my job. I locked the
fence." You leave your animal in the middle of a blazing sun,
it's going to look for a way to escape. And a חרש
שוטה וקטן cheiresh shoteh v'katan also are not sufficient ways of watching
it. In that case, ויצאה והזיקה חייב, v'yatzah v'hizikah chayav, you're liable.
מסרה Masara מסרה לרועה, masra lero'eh, if you gave it over to
a shepherd, נכנס הרועה תחתיו, nichnas haro'eh tachtav, then it becomes the
shepherd's responsibility. נפלה לגינה, nafla leginah,
let's say it accidentally fell into a garden. You were walking by
a רשות הרבים reshut harabim and on a high level and it
fell off, rolled down a cliff in רשות הרבים reshut harabim and
landed into somebody's garden. So you're an אונס, ones, okay.
You're not liable,
but nevertheless, so נהנית, nehenit, but it got benefit. Maybe it landed
and it cushioned its fall on top of some fruit in the
other person's yard. משלמת מה שנהנית, meshalemet mah shenehenit, you don't have
to pay for נזק, nezek, but you have to pay for the
benefit that you received. That's a concept that we've seen before, which
we can, if you might remember, the animal that eats fruit in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, people remember that? So you're פטור patur for
נזק nezek in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but the objective reality that
your animal got benefit, you have to pay the guy back for
giving your animal lunch.
Okay, so ירדה כדרכה והזיקה, yarda kedarka vehezika, if it just by
its own went into this guy's yard, so that's a classic שן
ברשות הניזק shen bireshut hanizak and it damaged, משלמת מה שהזיקה, meshalemet
mah shehezika, then you pay for the actual damage. כיצד משלמת מה
שהזיקה, keitzad meshalemet mah shehezika, how do you pay the amount of
damage? Now the reason it asks this question is because it's not
like it's eating some independent object, like eating some fruit in a
basket. It's eating fruit that's growing in a yard, you know, it's
eating wheat in the yard. So how do
you assess how to figure out the damage? שמין בית סאה באותה
שדה כמה הייתה יפה וכמה היא יפה. shamin beit se'ah be'ota sadeh
kama hayeta yafa vekama hi yafa.
So you take a look at a בית סאה, beit se'ah, which
we'll just call an acre, I don't know what it is, but
it's some unit of land and you say, how much was this
acre worth before the animal ate this grain and how much is
it worth after, right? Because then when you look at it in
the context of a much larger value and of a whole field,
the field doesn't get devalued directly based on the loss of the
actual value of the grain, right? So it's sort of like I
was giving the example when I think we did this a while
ago in the flip, like when you go ahead and you make
home improvements, it could cost you twenty-five thousand dollars to make home
improvements, it only increases the value of your house by five thousand
dollars or something, right? So the reality is that when you assess
something based on some things of much larger value, the difference in
the actual cost of that one object gets a little discounted. So
if you actually to say how much was the grain worth before
and after, you'd be paying sort of the full value of the
destroyed grain. But you're asking how much was the field worth, it's
going to be less. Now one of the reasons that you might
say that is the גמרא gemara is going to say it learns
it from a פסוק. pasuk. ובער בשדה אחר, uve'er bisdeh acher, it
consumes
in another field. It says שמין אותה על גב שדה אחר, shamin
ota al gav sadeh acher, you assess the value based on the
value of the field. One way of understanding that is that it's
actually saying that the ובער בשדה אחר uve'er bisdeh acher doesn't just
mean where it's doing the damage, but what you view of as
the object that was damaged. It consumes another field. So the thing
that's being damaged is the field, not the grain. So if you
look at it like it damaged my field rather than it damaged
my grain, you assess the difference in the value of the field.
Okay, רבי שמעון אומר, rabbi shimon omer, Rabbi Shimon says אכלה פירות
גמורים משלמת פירות גמורים. achla peirot gemurim meshalemet peirot gemurim.
When do you assess it in terms of the field? Not every
time something is growing. Only if it's growing and it hasn't been
fully ripened. But once the fruit is fully ripened, ready to be
harvested, then even though it's still attached, you there don't look like
it's damaging the field, you look like it's damaging the fruit and
you assess it in terms of the fruit. אם סאה סאה אם
סאתים סאתים. im se'ah se'ah im sa'atayim sa'atayim. So if it was
a bushel of grain and the grain was ready to be harvested,
you ask how much is a bushel of grain worth. If it's
two bushels, you ask two bushels. You don't ask how much was
the field worth before and after. So a lot of different things
in this משנה, mishnah, sort of wrap up stuff about שן ורגל
shen varegel moving from protecting it, which was issues that we saw
before about the שור shor and the בור bor we saw that
recently to this question of נהנית nehenit and to this question which
we've also seen in a different context, you know, this whole issue
of ליסטים listim and the role and רועה ro'eh and a שומר
shomer who takes responsibility. We also saw that about the גורח gore'ach
ox, about the שומר shomer who takes responsibility, and then finally the
question about how do you assess the damage. Okay, let's take a
look at the
גמרא. gemara. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught. איזהו כראוי ואיזהו שלא כראוי, eizehu kera'uy ve'eizehu shelo kera'uy, thank
you very much. What is considered to be a sufficient protecting of
the animal and not sufficient? דלת שיכולה לעמוד ברוח מצויה, delet sheyechola
la'amod beru'ach metzuya, if it's a
door, a fence that can withstand normal types of winds and you
could abstract that idea, normal types of occurrences. Okay, so that is
זהו כראוי, zehu kera'uy, that's an appropriate guarding of the animal.
שאינה יכולה לעמוד ברוח מצויה, she'eina yechola la'amod beru'ach metzuya, if it
can't withstand normal winds, normal types of things that might happen, that's
שלא כראוי. shelo kera'uy. Of course, then a question a little bit
it just displaces the question of how do you define מצויה, metzuya,
you know, but we get at least we're starting to get an
idea.
And just notice that רוח מצויה ru'ach metzuya is a stock phrase
that's already a category.
Right, right, that's right. רוח מצויה ruach metzuya does become
this
more abstract, sort of this more abstract standard,
right?
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now...
okay, so basically it means you have to... that's considered to be
minimal שמירה. shmira. Okay, less than רוח מצויה ruach metzuya is considered
פשיעה, pshia, gross negligence. Okay, now you could do it more... you
could stop things from being gross negligent and still not have made,
you know, sort of done a full שמירה shmira that would prevent
anything from going wrong. So basically what we're saying here is that
a minimum שמירה shmira is acceptable. Okay, that's the idea of רוח
מצויה. ruach metzuya. So the גמרא Gemara now wants to see how
does this match up with the other level of שמירה shmira that
we've known, that we've come to learn here from the other things.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמר רב מני בר פטיש. Amar Rav Mani bar Patish. Says מני
בר פטיש, Mani bar Patish, מאן תנא מועד דסגי ליה בשמירה פחותה?
man tanna muad de-sagi lei be-shmira pechuta? Now remember, שן ורגל shen
va-regel are a מועד. muad. They are considered habitual. Okay, now they're
not like a שור shor that might be, I mean depends on
what type of a שור מועד shor muad you have, like you
can imagine a מועד muad by a קרן keren that is like
has this vicious nature and is looking to break out and is
looking to go find animals to attack them. But I imagine even
most שוורים shors that are a מועד muad for נגיחות negichot means
that when they see another animal or they see something that enrages
them, it doesn't mean that if they're at home in their guarded
in their fence, they're going to be looking to break out. Okay,
so therefore, if it's... if you realize that, then it really is
a good basis for comparison. You have this שן ורגל, shen va-regel,
they're not like looking to do a jailbreak. You have a שור
shor that's a מועד, muad, it's not looking to do a jailbreak.
They're just animals that if they break out, there's a high likelihood
that they'll do some damage. Their normal sheep if it breaks out
is going to go graze somewhere. Okay, but it's not like it's...
it's not like it's got a כוונה kavana to break free. Okay,
but so therefore that's the question. So if this is sufficient for
an animal that has a propensity to damage if it breaks out,
okay, then presumably that should be the same level that you act
by a שור shor that's a מועד. muad. What is the level
of שמירה shmira required for an animal that if it were to
break out would have a propensity of damages? So we're saying here
that the answer is שמירה פחותה, shmira pechuta, minimum שמירה shmira suffices.
So let's take a look. אמר רב מני בר פטיש, Amar Rav
Mani bar Patish, מאן תנא מועד דסגי ליה בשמירה פחותה? man tanna
muad de-sagi lei be-shmira pechuta? Who's taught us that a מועד, muad,
that even though if it breaks out it'll pretty good likelihood it'll
cause damage, minimum שמירה shmira is enough? Because that's what we're saying
right now by שן ורגל. shen va-regel. So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבי יהודה היא. Rabbi Yehuda hi. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתנן,
De-tenan, because let's look at what we talk about a שור shor
that's a קרן מועד. keren muad. קשרו בעליו במוסירה, Kashro ba'alav be-mosira,
if the owner tied it up with a rope, ונעל לפניו כראוי,
ve-na'al le-fanav karaui, and they locked it appropriately—there's your again כראוי—ויצא והזיק,
and it went out and damaged, אחד תם ואחד מועד חייב דברי
רבי מאיר. echad tam ve-echad muad chayav divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says by a קרן מועד keren muad that's not sufficient,
minimum שמירה shmira is not sufficient, you're going to be liable. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, תם חייב מועד פטור. tam chayav muad
patur. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has that weird inverse position that a
תם tam minimum שמירה shmira you're still חייב, chayav, it's not enough.
But a מועד muad minimum שמירה shmira does suffice. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, ולא
ישמרנו בעליו, ve-lo yishmerenu ba'alav, and you
don't watch it after three times, then you're חייב. chayav. ושמור זה
הוא, Ve-shamur ze hu, once it's considered to be basically שמור shamur
even at a minimum level, you're exempt. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, still going by this קרן מועד, keren muad, אין לו שמירה
אלא סכין. ein lo shmira ela sakin. No, the only way that
you can watch an animal once it's a מועד muad is by
killing it. Okay, it's a question whether that means for liability or
just a general moral responsibility. Anyway, what we see is of those
three תנאים, Tannaim, the only one that says קרן מועד keren muad
suffices to do שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
So should we therefore infer that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the
author of our משנה, mishna, that it is the same by קרן
מועד keren muad as by שן ורגל מועד? shen va-regel muad? That's
the question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אפילו תימא רבי מאיר. Afilu teima Rabbi Meir. You know what, it
could be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that by קרן keren תם tam
and מועד muad require a high level. שן ורגל Shen va-regel a
lower level would suffice. Why?
שאני שן ורגל דתורה מיעטה בשמירתן. Shani shen va-regel de-Torah mi'ata bi-shmiratan.
שן ורגל Shen va-regel are different, not because of some logic, but
based on the פסוק. pasuk. The תורה Torah made it clear that
שן ורגל shen va-regel minimum שמירה shmira suffices. Where does the תורה
Torah make that clear from? דאמר רבי אלעזר, De-amar Rabbi Elazar, ואמרי
לה במתניתא תנא, ve-amrei lah be-matnita tana, some say we teach in
a ברייתא, beraita, ארבעה דברים התורה מיעטה בשמירתן. arba'ah devarim ha-Torah mi'ata
bi-shmiratan. There are four things that
the תורה Torah reduced the amount of שמירה shmira required, minimized the
amount of שמירה shmira required. ואלו הן, Ve-elu hen, these are they:
בור ואש שן ורגל. bor ve-esh shen va-regel. No, just seeing if
anybody was...
I had to do that.
Okay, בור ואש שן ורגל. bor ve-esh shen va-regel. So just seeing
if people are paying attention here. Okay, of the pit, the fire,
שן shen and רגל. regel. Now by the way, that's a lot.
What are the ארבעה אבות נזיקין arba'ah avot nezikin if you put
out אדם המזיק? adam ha-mazik? בור, bor, אש, esh, שן, shen, רגל,
regel, and קרן. keren. So three out of the four the תורה
Torah said minimum is enough. All those debates that we had in
that earlier משנה Mishna about קרן keren that maybe you need שמירה
מעולה, shmira me'ula, maybe no שמירה shmira is ever good enough, that's
just debates by קרן. keren. Everything else, minimum שמירה shmira is okay.
Okay, let's take a look how we know it and then we
could ask why.
Okay, בור דכתיב, bor dechsiv,
by the pit because it says, כי יפתח איש בור או כי
יכרה איש בור ולא יכסנו, ki yiftach ish bor o ki yichreh
ish bor velo yichasenu, if you dig or you uncover and you
don't cover it, הכיסוי פטור, hakisui patur, once you've covered it, all
of a sudden he's even cover it and a cover suffices. הכיסוי
פטור. hakisui patur. Obviously it has to be, you know, a real
cover, it has to withstand again רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, but any
minimum cover suffices. אש, eish, fire, דכתיב, dechsiv, שלם ישלם המבעיר את
הבערה, shaleim yeshaleim hamavir es hab'eira, he who shall surely pay the
one who lights the conflagration, עד דעביד כעין מבעיר, ad de'avid k'ein
mavir, until you're considered like the one who actually consciously lit it,
like as if you torched the place. If you did a minimum
שמירה, shmira, if you're if you're not grossly negligent, we say it's
like you intentionally did it. Okay, but if you're not, if you
did if you basically remove, you know, gross negligence, you're not like
you're actually torched the place. Okay, עד דעביד כעין מבעיר. ad de'avid
k'ein mavir. שן, shein, by the by the tooth, דכתיב, dechsiv, וביער
בשדה אחר, uvi'eir besadeh acher, it consumes in another field, עד דעביד
כעין וביער. ad de'avid k'ein uvi'eir. So that idea is like is
as if you, not just the animal consumed, but like you consumed.
You were so negligent it's like you made it happen. Okay, רגל,
regel, דכתיב, dechsiv, by רגל regel it says,
ושיחל, v'shilach, you should send forth and he sends forth the consumer,
ושיחל את בעירה, v'shilach es be'iro, remember when we said that that
means a רגל, regel, עד דעביד כעין ושיחל, ad de'avid k'ein v'shilach,
until it's like you sent the animal consciously to do it. You
were really negligent. Okay, ותניא ושיחל זה הרגל, v'sanya v'shilach zeh haregel,
and to remind us of going back to like the way beginning
of the מסכת, maseches, you sent forth your consumer, ושיחל v'shilach means
the רגל, regel, וכן הוא אומר, v'chein hu omer, משלח רגל השור
והחמור, mishale'ach regel hashor vehachamor, the one who sends forth the leg
of the ox and the donkey, וביער uvi'eir consumes, זה השן, zeh
hashein, that's the tooth, וכן הוא אומר, v'chein hu omer, כאשר יבער
הגלל עד תומו, ka'asher yiva'er hagalal ad tumo, until until the the
thing consumes until completion. טעמא דעביד כעין ושיחל וביער, tama de'avid k'ein
v'shilach uvi'eir, the only reason you're חייב chayav is if it's like
you sent it forth, you made it
consume. הא לא עביד לא, ha lo avid lo, if you didn't,
not. Okay, let's just read the סוגיא sugia and then we'll discuss
why the logic behind this. Okay, אמר רבה, amar Rava, says רבה,
Rava, מתניתין נמי דיקא, masnisin nami dika, this also can be inferred
from the language of the משנה Mishna that שן ורגל shein varegel
is not like קרן keren and this lower level of שמירה shmira
is specific by שן ורגל. shein varegel. דקתני, dekasni, because the משנה
Mishna says, צאן, tzon, that you brought your sheep into the pen.
מכדי, michdi, why do we all of a sudden switch from ox
to sheep? בשור עסקינן ואתי, beshor askinan va'asi, we've been talking about
ox for the last thirty דף. daf. What are all of a
sudden talking about sheep? ניתני שור, nisni shor, want to talk about
locking up your ox. מאי שנא דקתני צאן, mai shna dekasni tzon,
why are we talking about sheep? לאו משום דהתם מיעטה בשמירתן? lav
mishum de-hasam mi'atah b'shmirasan? Because we want to say that the watching
of sheep, you know, it would be true ox too of the
שן ורגל shein varegel of ox, but classically a sheep is not
going goring. Sheep is a classic, like, you know, concept of שן
ורגל. shein varegel. So, לאו משום דהתם קרן לא כתיבא בה, lav
mishum de-hasam keren lo kesiva bah, שן ורגל הוא דכתיבא בה. shein
varegel hu deksiva bah.
קרן keren is not written by sheep, right? It doesn't talk in
the תורה Torah about a sheep goring. It talks about but a
sheep is the animal that goes and eats. So קא משמע לן
דשן ורגל מועדין הן, ka mashma lan d'shein varegel mu'adin hein, שן
ורגל shein varegel although they're מועד, mu'ad, nevertheless minimum שמירה shmira is
enough. שמע מינה, shma mina, that is a good inference. So the
only thing you require a high level of שמירה shmira for is
קרן, keren, anything else once you've done minimum you're exempt. Now the
question is why? What makes these things different? So the natural thing
to think about is like to what degree are you creating a,
you know, danger to society? But that really doesn't make so much
sense because if you think about it, like if we think about
degree of danger, like a fire that gets out of hand or
deep well could cause loss of life, you know, at least as
much I would imagine as a goring ox. I imagine even oxen
that are מועד mu'ad to gore are not going out and doing
it so regularly, right? Like I mean they normally need some provocation,
I mean I'm just speaking out of speculation but that's my sense,
whereas if you think about really an a fire or well that's
a real hazard, I mean that could be a real much bigger,
you know, number one for likelihood that somebody would be injured, the
severity of the injury, it's hard to understand why of all why
why the תורה Torah would go lighter by that than it would
by the watching of your ox. The other thing maybe you could
suggest is like I was saying before but I was discounting is
that maybe an ox because it's a live being will more try
to break through of some type of a שמירה. shmira. So if
it's not just a מועד mu'ad to gore when it sees an
animal, but it actually has a vicious nature and it's looking like
to break through, maybe then you could understand why an ox more
than a well, although a fire, you know, fire is also live
in a different way and it's very hard to control a fire.
So So and even that I don't believe that every ox that's
a מועד muad is looking to break through of its of its
of its cage. It's like when it's provoked it'll do something. So
it's very hard, if you were just to base on the propensity
and the likelihood and the severity of the damage, why you should
need שמירה shmira more by קרן keren versus שן ורגל shen v'regel
and every other thing else. I think the answer is probably already
in the language of the גמרא. gemara. The גמרא gemara says that
for all of these פסוקים psukim it says why you need a
lower level. It says עד דעביד כעין ובער, ad d'avid k'ein u'bi'er,
עד דעביד ושלח, ad d'avid v'shilach, עד דעביד, ad d'avid, you know,
but by the בור bor it doesn't say that. But the point
being, and this gets back to the early questions about, you know,
why you're חייב chayav when your things go out and damage. Here
the גמרא's gemara conceptualizing it as: you know why we make you
pay when your animal eats? 'Cause it's like you did it. You
know why we make you pay when your fire goes out? 'Cause
it's like you torched the place. Oh, it was an accident. I
was just having a barbecue, I wasn't paying attention. It doesn't matter.
You were so negligent, it's as if you did it yourself. It's
as if you sent your animal to do it. Right? So if
the model is we have to make it like as if you
did it, we need a high degree of negligence. So why should
שור shor be different? Because שור shor with כוונתו להזיק kavanato l'hazik
is the one case where you have something that's defined as an
act of נזק nezek on its own terms. We don't have to
ascribe it to you and say it's like you tried to destroy
that person's thing. Your animal had the כוונה להזיק. kavana l'hazik. So
it itself was an act of מזיק mazik just in terms of
the act the animal was doing. So basically what it seems like
we're saying is, in order to make somebody pay, there has to
be something that we can label intentional damage, an act of מזיק.
mazik. So in the case of קרן, keren, the ox did an
intentional act of מזיק mazik and you had some degree of fault.
Maybe you did a minimum שמירה, shmira, but you had some degree
of fault. Once you start with an intentional act of מזיק, mazik,
we can make you pay because you should've, because you didn't do
the maximum שמירה shmira possible. But by everything else, there was no
conscious act of מזיק. mazik. Right? Somebody fell into the בור, bor,
the fire escaped, the animal was just nibbling, you know, it wasn't
an act of מזיק. mazik. So to make it an act of
מזיק, mazik, there has to be a high degree of negligence that
we can say it's as if you were so grossly negligent it's
like you intentionally did it, as if you did it. So that
seems to be a very interesting way of getting at this. Right?
Again, our natural thing, if we, you know, had not been learning
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, like, why should any of this matter? I
still don't really understand why. Like, you know, you were negligent. We
should be looking at the likelihood of damage, the severity of the
injury, how big of a hazard it was, etc. But the גמרא's
gemara working with these formal categories and here it's introducing a new
idea. You start with the idea of a מעשה מזיק, ma'aseh mazik,
intentional
willful damage. By the קרן keren you always have that. So as
long as there's a little negligence, we're going to make you pay.
By these other things, you don't have that and therefore you need
high negligence so it's so negligent it's as if you wanted it
to happen, as if you did it. All right. So that's the
sort of approach I would take on this גמרא.
gemara. Yeah, I liked it, like with the כסוי, kisuy, you know,
if the camels have come and stuff like that. All of that
seemed like we were talking about gross negligence. It was sort of
like, you
know, you have to use basic common sense, like, right, meaning maybe
I'm a little overstating by gross negligence, but still, it's negligence as
opposed to, you know, there's a range between I'm no longer negligent,
you're right, maybe I'm a little overstating by using the word gross
negligence, but still, but there's a range between I'm not negligent but
I'm not really being totally... right, meaning... right, meaning כראוי karaui maybe
gets beyond just gross negligence and I'm not really negligent but I'm
still not being totally protect, totally preventing things from happening. I'm not
being as careful as I could be. Okay. All right. So yeah,
I might have overstated a little with the word gross negligence. All
right, so let's continue. Now we move on to another set of
fascinating things, which as you'll see is indirectly connected to the משנה.
mishna. תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, אמר רבי יהושע:
amar Rabbi Yehoshua: ארבעה דברים העושה אותם פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני
שמיים. arba'ah devarim ha'oseh otam patur mi'dinei adam v'chayav bi'dinei shamayim. Four
things, somebody who does them is exempt from, you know, from a
human court and liable up in heaven, which could, you know, understand's
mean, I mean you could make that as a total theological statement,
God will pay you back, but it's also a question about like,
you know, it's a way of saying that there's actually some moral
responsibility and it does become an interesting question like, does, can that
translate into, if I want to get out of my חיוב בדיני
שמיים, chiyuv bi'dinei shamayim, maybe the way I do it is by
paying you back for what I've done to you, right? Does that
create a sense of a practical religious slash moral responsibility to rectify,
you know, even here on this earth? Okay. ואלו הן, v'elu hen,
these are they: הפורץ גדר בפני בהמת חבירו, ha'poretz geder bifnei behemet
chaveiro, somebody who breaks the fence in front of your friend's animal.
So that's going to the משנה, mishna, right? By the לסטים listim
who break the fence and then presumably the animal goes out and
gets lost. So, I don't do anything. Okay, I'll pay you back
for your fence, you know, I didn't actually steal your animal, I
didn't injure your animal, I'm just a גרמא. grama. So you're פטור
בדיני אדם. patur bedinei adam. Okay, הכופף קמתו של חברו בפני הדליקה,
ha-kofef kamato shel chavero bifnei ha-dleika, or there's a fire and you
basically you just push somebody's haystack in front of a sheaf of
grain in front of the fire and then the fire comes ten
minutes later and destroys it. I didn't destroy it, I just moved
it into the street. Okay, so השוכר עדי שקר להעיד, ha-socher edei
sheker leha-id, so somebody who hires false witnesses. Right, it's pretty interesting,
right? The witnesses themselves are עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. The person who
hires the false witnesses, actually there's no way you can sue them.
Okay, why? I mean it's what are you talking about? אין שליח
לדבר עבירה. ein shliach lidvar aveira. So what? I paid them money.
It was their decision to actually do it, you know. And והיודע
עדות לחברו ואינו מעיד לו. ve-ha-yodeya edut le-chavero ve-eino me-id lo. This
one is the big, maybe the biggest חידוש chidush because it's the
most passive. You know testimony that can help your friend in a
court and you don't come and testify. So just the passive withholding
of information that could help somebody is a פטור בדיני שמיים. patur
bedinei shamayim. I mean it's funny, it's a חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav
bedinei shamayim. There's a פסוק pasuk that says explicitly that you can't
withhold testimony. אם לוא יגיד ונשא עוונו. im lo yagid ve-nasa avono.
Right, so that's if somebody actually made you take a שבועה shvua
to come and do it. But anyway, but there might be some
religious fault, you might transgress some איסור, issur, but you can't be
sued for compensation. The פטור בדיני אדם patur bedinei adam here, we're
talking totally in a בבא קמא Bava Kamma context. Can I seek
compensation for the loss that this person has caused me? Right, but
that's a good point. Meaning some of these things, you know, maybe
you're עובר over on some איסור, issur, you know, but we're talking
here about the compensation question. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. אמר מר, הפורץ גדר בפני בהמת חברו. amar mar, ha-poretz
geder bifnei behemot chavero. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case that
if you break the fence you're going to be פטור בדיני אדם?
patur bedinei adam? אילימא בכותל ברי, eileima be-kotel bari, if it's a
strong fence, בדיני אדם נמי ליחייב, bedinei adam nami le-chayev, you'd also
be חייב chayav by דיני אדם. dinei adam. We'll get back to
that in a minute. אלא בכותל רעוע, ela be-kotel ra'u'a, it must
be a weak fence. Now why are you חייב chayav for a
strong fence? So you look at רש״י. Rashi. What does רש״י Rashi
say why you're חייב? chayav? רש״י Rashi says, בכותל ברי בדיני אדם
נמי ליחייב, be-kotel bari bedinei adam nami le-chayev, four lines three lines
on the bottom רש״י Rashi says, ברי, מיהא כותל, bari, miya ha-kotel,
you should at least have to pay for breaking the fence, דהא
בידיים עביד, de-ha be-yadayim avid, you did it directly. So why are
you... the word פטור patur means you're פטור patur on everything. Okay,
so you're not פטור patur on everything if it was a strong
fence, at least pay for the fence. גבי בהמה ליכא למימר דליחייב,
gabei behema leika le-meimar de-li-chayev, but רש״י Rashi says you can't say
that if you broke a strong fence you're חייב chayav for the
בהמה. behema. דתנן, פרצוהו ליסטים פטור. de-tnan, partzu-hu listim patur. The משנה
mishna says that. That's why it's worth mentioning this discussion, because the
משנה mishna discusses breaking a fence and it says that the ליסטים
listim are פטור. patur. So רש״י Rashi says the only thing you're
חייב chayav for is for the fence. Now there are two other
opinions in ראשונים rishonim that go against this. One is a תוספות,
Tosafot, not here but elsewhere, says you are חייב chayav for the
loss of the animal, but not... how does it work with the
משנה? mishna? Because the משנה mishna says the ליסטים listim are פטור,
patur, not if the animal wanders off and gets lost. The משנה
mishna is פטור patur for the נזק nezek that the animal does.
There's no reason for the owners of the animal to be חייב
chayav for the נזק nezek unless they physically take possession. But if
the animal wanders off and gets lost, maybe you would be חייב.
chayav. Now it's not exactly clear. Okay, you could make that distinction.
Yes, this doesn't contradict the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna is talking
about חייב chayav for damage that it does. This could be talking
that you're חייב chayav for if it gets lost. But it doesn't
explain what the basis of the חיוב chiyuv is. What do you
mean? I'm not a מזיק, mazik, I'm not a גנב, ganav, why
am I חייב? chayav? That you'd think it's a גרמא, grama, I
indirectly caused it, right? So it's not easy to understand what the
conceptual basis... forget the problem of the משנה, mishna, forget the משנה.
mishna. If it means you're חייב chayav for the lost animal, right,
again, why is this not just your classic גרמה בנזיקין? grama be-nezikin?
Okay, so that again explains why רש״י Rashi would say it's talking
about the fence. רמב״ם, Rambam, and there's actually a תשובה teshuva of
the רמב״ם Rambam on this question, just to show you know that
sometimes the רמב״ם Rambam wrote תשובות teshuvot about purely... I mean, I
don't know how many people were פוסק posk-ing this, but it was
like very... there's actually, I think it's the חכמי לוניל, Chachmei Lunel,
because the רמב״ם Rambam says you're חייב chayav for the נזק nezek
the animal does when it's a good fence. And the people said,
how could you say that? The משנה mishna says that the ליסטים
listim are פטור. patur. And the רמב״ם Rambam basically says that the
answer, he says this in a תשובה, teshuva, is that the answer
is as to whether the ליסטים listim are trying, whether you're trying
to have the animal go and do damage. If I just break
the fence because I don't know, I'm trying to steal your animal,
whatever I'm doing, I'm trying to get into your place, and incidentally
the animal goes off and does damage, it's not my animal, I'm
not חייב chayav for the damage it does. But if I break
your fence because I want it to go ahead and damage somebody
else's property, then I am actually חייב chayav for the damage that
it does. Now, again, it's not exactly understood clearly why. Is that
an אדם המזיק? adam ha-mazik? It's a גרמא. grama. Am I an
owner of the animal? I didn't take possession. Right, I just think
that when you have that כוונה, kavana, you want to use the...
you want the animal to perform an action for you, right, then
you become like the owner of it. It's a קניין. kinyan. Right,
so that could be... that seems to be the idea behind the
רמב״ם. Rambam. What type? Because you don't have to be the property
owner of an animal. Remember, a שומר shomer is חייב chayav for
the נזק, nezek, a גנב ganav is חייב chayav for the נזק.
nezek. Now all of those do an act that's considered taking possession
of the thing. Not taking ownership, but taking possession. When you break
the fence you don't take possession, but is the very constructing of
the situation and desire to use it to damage somebody else like
a type of a, it's my animal for נזק, nezek, and you're
חייב chayav for the נזק. nezek. So that is how the רמב"ם
Rambam reads this, okay? But again, רש"י Rashi reads this very narrowly,
you're just חייב chayav for the wall. So the answer is, it's
a rickety wall. It's a rickety wall, there's no חיוב chiyuv for
breaking it, it wasn't worth anything anyway, and in terms of the
other approaches, it was such a rickety wall that the animal could
have broken through on its own, so you didn't really create the
opportunity for the animal to get lost or to damage, cause the
animal could have easily just broken through on its own. What? רעועה.
Re'ua. רעועה. Re'ua. Rickety. Okay. All right. Let us just go three
more lines to the dots. אמר מר. Amar mar. הכופף קומתו של
חבירו בפני הדליקה היכי דמי? Hakofef komato shechavero bifnei hadeleika heychei dami?
What's the case that you're פטור patur בדיני אדם b'dinei adam וחייב
v'chayav בדיני שמים b'dinei shamayim if you put the sort of sheaf
in front of the sheaf, sheaf, sheaf in front of the fire?
So, אילימא ee-leyma דמטי d'mati ברוח מצויה, b'ruach metzuya, that you put
it by a fire and the fire is going to reach it
in a, that good old רוח מצויה. ruach metzuya. So it's expected
that the fire will reach it, so בדיני אדם נמי ניחייב, b'dinei
adam nami nichayiv, you should also be חייב chayav for בדיני אדם
dinei adam because, now we'll discuss why in a minute. אלא Ella
דמטי d'mati ברוח שאינה מצויה. b'ruach she'eino metzuya. Okay, you put it
in front of a fire, it was unlikely the fire would reach
it but lo and behold it did. So therefore you're not חייב
chayav בדיני אדם b'dinei adam but you're חייב chayav בדיני שמים. b'dinei
shamayim. ורב אשי אמר, Ve'rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says,
טמון איתמר. tomun itmar. No, no, no, the case here is not
a case of making the fire burn it, it's of burying it.
משום דשוייה טמון באש. Mishum d'shavye tomun b'eish. You made it something
buried in the fire. What does that mean? We're going to learn
later in this פרק perek that if a fire burns something down
and it burns something that was hidden, like not exposed, that the
owner of the fire is exempt. So here you go, so, David's
fire is breaking out into Chanan's yard, it's about to burn down
Chanan's piles of grain, and
I, I don't like Chanan so much but I really like David.
So what I do is I take a blanket and I throw
it over Chanan's pile of grain. So now David's fire burns it
down and you don't have to pay because it was all טמון,
tomun, it was all buried. I allowed it to be in that
loophole of liability. So in that case, Chanan lost out on his
being compensated because I did this טובה tova and I put it
under a blanket. So that would be the case of פטור patur
בדיני אדם b'dinei adam וחייב v'chayav בדיני שמים. b'dinei shamayim. I just
want to say one thing though about the דמטי mati ברוח מצויה.
b'ruach metzuya. If I go ahead and I take your sheaf of
wheat and I put it in front of a fire that's burning
and it's going to get here in five minutes and it's definitely
going to get here, and the גמרא Gemara says I'm חייב, chayav,
what category am I חייב chayav for? Like, what type of an
act was it? Am I חייב chayav because of אש? eish? Am
I חייב chayav because of אדם המזיק? adam hamazik? What would you
say? Understand the scenario? I take your thing, I take your sheaf
of grain, and I put it, there's a fire over there and
the wind is blowing it and it's going to get here in
five minutes and I put it here and I walk away, and
five minutes later the fire burns it down and the גמרא Gemara
says I'm חייב. chayav. What am I חייב chayav for? Well, I
didn't do anything with the fire, I mean I put it there,
I walked away. So it was going to be a רוח
מצויה.
ruach
metzuya.
Okay. So I would say you're
חייב chayav for אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. I would say you put
it in a scenario which is about to, so, it's like you
directly destroyed it, right? But תוספות Tosafot seems to think, and then
it becomes interesting questions about would you be חייב chayav for רציחה?
retzicha? Right, there's a גמרא Gemara that says if you tie somebody
up in front of a fire and the fire kills them, you're
not חייב chayav for רציחה. retzicha. So תוספות Tosafot says that's only
if the person was already there and you just stopped them from
moving. But if you actually bound somebody up, it's like the old,
like the guy, the dastardly guy puts them on the train tracks,
if someone was already on the train tracks and you stopped them
from moving, you'd be פטור patur because you just kept the situation.
But if you put someone on the train tracks and the train
came, that would be like an act of רציחה. retzicha. So it's
not that you're חייב chayav for אש, eish, it's that then you,
by putting somebody, actively putting them in the scenario where now something
is about to and definitely going to happen, it's like you directly
threw them in the fire. But that's interesting, right, whether this, תוספות
Tosafot sort of plays with that question, would that be a type
of a חייב chayav for אש eish or would you be חייב
chayav for an אדם המזיק? adam hamazik? I think it would clearly
be an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. Okay.